<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter of Meric Casaubon D.D. &amp;c to Peter du Moulin D.D. and prebendarie of the same church concerning natural experimental philosophie, and some books lately set out about it.</title>
            <title>Letter of Meric Casaubon to Peter du Moulin concerning natural experimental philosophie</title>
            <author>Casaubon, Meric, 1599-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35559</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C805</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17546</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13161400</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13161400</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98192</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35559)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98192)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 449:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter of Meric Casaubon D.D. &amp;c to Peter du Moulin D.D. and prebendarie of the same church concerning natural experimental philosophie, and some books lately set out about it.</title>
                  <title>Letter of Meric Casaubon to Peter du Moulin concerning natural experimental philosophie</title>
                  <author>Casaubon, Meric, 1599-1671.</author>
                  <author>Du Moulin, Peter, 1601-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Mordgen ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Physics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98192:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98192:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER OF MERIC CASAUBON D.D. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> TO <hi>Peter du Moulin</hi> D.D. and Prebendarie of the ſame Church: Concerning Natural experimental Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie, and ſome books lately ſet out about it.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>ALMA MATER CANTA<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>BRIGIA</head>
               <q>HINC LUCEM ET POCULA SACRA</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Printed for WILLIAM MORDEN Bookſeller. 1669.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:98192:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98192:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou have not forgotten, I dare ſay, (it is not ſo long ſince) where and when you were pleaſed to beſtow a Viſit upon me, two young Univerſitie men being then with me; and you came with a book in your hand, and delivered it to me with a ſmiling countenance, which, as ſoon as I had opened the book, I did interpret, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving already conteſted with you more then once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame matter, as though by it you hoped to ſtop my mouth for ever. I cannot ſay you did intend it ſo really: but ſo I did interpret it then; but it did fall out much otherwiſe. For after I had opened it, by the very Title of it, I was much confirmed in my former opinion, and profeſſed it ſo to you, which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned much diſcourſe between us until I was weary, and (as my condition is now) ſomewhat ſpent. Ever ſince that, what I now write, hath been in my mind, and I have had thoughts to impart it to you long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though ſtill ſomewhat hath diverted me. The matter in agitation between us (I need not tell you, I know) was: whether this way of Philoſophy, of late years much cried up in <hi>London</hi> and elſewhere; was, as ſet out by ſome, more likely to prove advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous, or prejudicial, if not deſtructive, to good learning: by which I mean, (not excluding natural Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy) what in former ages of the world, and by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98192:3"/>many to this day (by you alſo I make no queſtion) hath been and is accounted true, ſolid, uſeful learning: which hath been cheriſhed and countenanced by Kings and Princes and Publick States, in their generations, in all places of Europe hitherto; and hath gotten credit and admiration to the Owners and Profeſſours of it du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their lives, and after their death, immortal fame.</p>
            <p>But before I enter upon the buſineſs, I muſt make my way by removing of a block, which I meet with artificially laid by ſome, to fright us in our progreſs, and hinder the freedom of our enquiry. It is this: Whether it be not a breach, if not of Allegiance, yet of that reſpect and reverence we ow to the <hi>Royal Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> to except againſt any thing that is done, or writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by any, who profeſs themſelves of the <hi>Royal So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety?</hi> I ſhould not make ſuch a queſtion, but that I find juſt occaſion, as I conceive. I do not well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the full extent of that ſpeech, uſed by ſome, <hi>to diminiſh the Royal Society. Diminutio,</hi> in the Civil Law, you know, is a very comprehenſive word, and reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to many things. Were it but a breach of good manners, and civility; or, as they ſpeak, <hi>want of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and breeding,</hi> I would be loth to be guilty of it. But God forbid, that ſuch reaſoning ſhould paſs for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, in good earneſt. That his <hi>Majeſty</hi> would ſo far encourage any kind of learning, as not onely to be the <hi>FOUNDER,</hi> but ſtyle Himſelf the <hi>PATRON</hi> alſo of ſuch a <hi>Society,</hi> is an act well becoming the magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of a great King, and to be entertained with hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt acknowledgements by all that pretend to learning. But to intereſt that <hi>Sacred name,</hi> in every thing, or any thing that is done, or written by any, that have the honour to be of that <hi>Society,</hi> though commended to us
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98192:3"/>under the title of good and profitable learning, I think is not juſtifiable: neither is the whole <hi>Society,</hi> as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, concerned (except it be owned by expreſs autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the whole body) in what is done by any one or more members of the <hi>Society:</hi> it being very poſſible, that many, who even in thoſe things that concern learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and knowledge in general, are of different judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and opinions, may yet agree in ſomewhat ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to juſtifie their title to this <hi>Royal Foundation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give me leave to inſiſt a little (for it is a tender point) upon the danger, or unreaſonableneſs of ſuch remote inferences. <hi>Daily publick Prayers,</hi> you know, were at firſt inſtituted by Primitive Chriſtians, as the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate ſervice of Almighty God: grounding, not onely upon the practice of the Church, under the Law; but alſo upon the words of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul: <hi>I exhort therefore</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for kings, and all that are in authority, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſs and honeſty:</hi> and that the peace and welfare of kingdoms, the honour and ſafety of Kings and Princes, did very much depend on the due and daily performance of that <hi>Service,</hi> was ſo general a belief in thoſe days of exemplary piety, that we read of heathen Princes and Emperours, who, though not Chriſtians otherwiſe, yet have had ſo much faith and Chriſtianity, as to commend their ſafety to the Church upon that account. This, if you pleaſe, you may find out of good records of antiquity ſufficiently proved and atteſted, in a little Treatiſe <hi>Of the uſe of Daily Publick Prayers;</hi> written by me ſomewhat haſtily, to help a learned Biſhop againſt a pack of bold and confident Adverſaries: ſent by me to the late Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and learned Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh;</hi> and by him, at the requeſt of that learned Biſhop, ſhortly after ſent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98192:4"/>to the Preſs. In England, beſide the authority of ſuch Precedents, and of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls <hi>Exhortation,</hi> or inſtitution: that ſuch a <hi>Service</hi> is eſtabliſhed by the Authority of Kings (who alſo may in ſome reſpect, becauſe of thoſe many Cathedrals of their foundation, where it is moſt duly and ſolemnly performed, be ſtyled <hi>Founders</hi> of it in this kingdom:) and Parliaments, who knoweth not? Now, (to paſs by the conſequence of the Royal Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and what the wilful contempt of it may amount to) I ask: The honour, ſafety and proſperity of Kings, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the belief of thoſe Primitive Chriſtians, whom all true Chriſtians, profeſs to honour and reverence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much concerned in thoſe <hi>Prayers;</hi> would it be charitable hence to infer, that none love the King truly, and ſtudy his ſafety, but thoſe that love and frequent them, when not otherwiſe lawfully let or hindred? That ſome hate and forbear them upon that account, (factious men otherwiſe, and Fanaticks, or openly ſchiſmatical) I make no queſtion: but to make a general concluſion of it, when we know that the ſame effect may proceed ſometimes from very different cauſes, would argue, I think, great want of judgement and diſcretion, and as great, if not greater, of charity. With much more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I conclude, that a man may write againſt the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of ſome of the <hi>Royal Society;</hi> yea and cenſure them as they may deſerve, without any reflection at all upon the <hi>Royal Founder,</hi> or <hi>Royal Society</hi> in general.</p>
            <p>In the next place, what made me judge of the Book, as I did, at the firſt opening of it, by ſome words in the Title-page, though probably I might tell you then, yet I will now further explain my ſelf. I obſerved there, <hi>Practical uſeful learning,</hi> appropriated to the way now in uſe, by experiments: and thoſe that go any other
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98192:4"/>way, and follow other ſtudies, which have been formerly in requeſt, ſtyled, <hi>men of the Notional way.</hi> By <hi>Practical uſeful learning, Chymiſtry</hi> and the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> as the Author doth explain himſelf, are alſo comprehended; whatſoever is beſides, ſo far as I can underſtand by the book, is proſcribed, as <hi>uſeleſs, notional</hi> and <hi>unprofitable.</hi> I had obſerved it before in another book, written by a learned man, a great admirer and abetter of <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Philoſophy,</hi> who ſpeaks of the Ancients, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient learning with a ſhew of much more reſpect and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration: but in effect, to the ſame purpoſe, to cry down all other ſtudies and learning, ordinarily compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended under the title of <hi>humane learning,</hi> to be but <hi>umbratick</hi> things, <hi>verbal</hi> things, of little or no uſe, ſince this new light of <hi>true real Knowledge</hi> eſpecially. Now, what other arguments need they, either to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the credit of their way, and of that way they commend to us; or to cry down any other way that hath hitherto been in requeſt; then to make the world beleeve, that it is of <hi>no uſe?</hi> You know what judgement was paſs'd againſt <hi>the fig-tree, that bare no fruit:</hi> And that <hi>earth</hi> or ground, which <hi>inſtead of herbs meet for the uſe of men, beareth nothing but thorns and bryers,</hi> (<hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting</hi> and <hi>wrangling,</hi> in their phraſe) is pronounced by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul, <hi>accurſed,</hi> and <hi>worthy to be burned.</hi> But, I ask; what is it that theſe account <hi>uſeful,</hi> and <hi>uſeleſs?</hi> For if nothing muſt be accounted <hi>uſeful,</hi> (as ſome ſeem to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine) but what doth afford ſome uſe for the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or conveniencies of this preſent life; I do not know but that a Brewer, or a Baker, a skilful Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leech, or a Smith, or the like, may conteſt in point of true worth or deſert with many, who for their learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as then thought, have been reputed generally, the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98192:5"/>great Lights and Ornaments of their age: though ſuch, as never medled in their writings with experimental philoſophy. They that beleeve that man doth conſiſt of two chief parts, the body and a ſoul, whereof the ſoul the more noble and more conſiderable part, as even Heathens moſt of them have determined it: natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral reaſon will oblige them to beleeve, that a greater ſhare of care and proviſion doth belong to that which is immortal, from the right ordering of which all true happineſs, preſent or future, doth depend; then to that which is mortal, and naturally brutiſh, and of little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance. Thoſe men therefore, who have applied themſelves by their writings to promote vertue and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, in their kind, (that is, ſo far as God was known to them) were generally thought to have deſerved of mankind, as well (if not better) as the moſt renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed inventours, or promoters of uſeful Arts or Trades. Had <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> never written any thing but his <hi>Ethicks,</hi> (that incomparable piece) he deſerved the thanks of all ages; and I make no queſtion but in all ages, even ſince Chriſtianity, many thouſands have reaped the fruit of that incomparable work, which alone is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent where it meets with right palats to ſpeak its worth; but compared with others, that have written of that argument ſince, and have not troden in his paths, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes more illuſtrious. I might ſay the ſame of thoſe <hi>Aurea Carmina,</hi> which are attributed to <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> and which <hi>Galen</hi> (that excellent both Philoſopher and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician) had in ſuch eſteem, that he did not onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them to others, as a ſovereign antidote againſt the diſeaſes of the mind, but himſelf doth profeſs of himſelf, that he was wont firſt to read, but afterwards to repeat them once or twice every day, for the benefit
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98192:5"/>he reaped by them. So of <hi>Cebes</hi> his <hi>Table:</hi> of <hi>Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro's Offices:</hi> and (not to name others) of <hi>Epictetus</hi> his <hi>Enchiridion,</hi> though much later then ſome of the reſt, yet not inferiour unto any. And here, by the way; both by him and ſome others that have written up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, we may find this very point excellently well handled; Whether thoſe men who make it their work to reclaim men from that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>cloſe adherence</hi> of the mind to the body and ſenſes (which moſt men are naturally prone to) to the care and culture of their ſouls, ought in reaſon to be accounted <hi>unprofitable</hi> to the Common-wealth; or rather, of all Profeſſions, the moſt <hi>uſeful</hi> and neceſſary. I wiſh ſome of our <hi>Mechanicks,</hi> who are ſo highly conceited of their way, laying aſide prejudice and preengagement (if they can) would take the pains to read thoſe admirable diſcourſes: it may be they would find, that the ſway of the times, more then any weight of right reaſon, hath led them hitherto, into this opinion.</p>
            <p>But alas! poor <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> your Author will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of above three books of his to be worth the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and his <hi>Ethicks</hi> is none of them. And elſewhere he doth queſtion, whether thoſe works, generally aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedto <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> were, or are his indeed? whereby we may gueſs, though he have written againſt him, he ſaith, how well he was read in <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> Elſe, the ſtyle of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſo conſtant to it ſelf every where, and in a manner unimitable; but much more the matter ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and rational every where almoſt, would eaſily have convinced him. But certainly the light account he makes of him all along, reproaching his adverſary ſo often, for his love to and eſteem of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> would make a man admire what account he made of himſelf. I think
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98192:6"/>he had done well, before he had taken ſuch a task upon himſelf, to have made it appear (the eaſier task of the two, as I conceive) that all men that have been fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in former ages, for their judgement, wit and learning, were no ſuch thing really as they appeared unto the world, but meer <hi>Idols</hi> and <hi>Phantaſms,</hi> not true rational men, ſuch as this latter age hath produced; and their judgement therefore not at all to be regarded. Then indeed we might with more patience, and equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity hear what he hath to ſay againſt <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> for ſound and ſolid reaſon, and for all manner of knowledge attainable by meer man without divine revelation, the wonder of all ages hitherto. But not to inſiſt on former ages, I will name but one man of very freſh memory; What, do you think that <hi>Julius Caeſar Scaliger,</hi> for learning and judgement, may be put in the balance to be weighed with your Author? <hi>Vir propter excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentem omnium diſciplinarum eruditionem admiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus:</hi> So <hi>Pererius,</hi> that learned and judicious Jeſuite of him: and ſo, ſo many others, that a man out of all kind of writers might eaſily ſwell a book into a great volume of teſtimonies concerning that admirable man. He had read <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> to the purpoſe, it ſeems, again and again, by the uſe that he makes of him upon every occaſion: but ſeldom names him without ſome intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of higheſt admiration and veneration, that can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Idolatry be deferred unto man. And what think you of meer Naturaliſts, ſuch as <hi>Laurentius, Fabricius ab Aquapendente, Caſſerius Placentinus,</hi> (I name them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have them by me at this time) and the like? Will their teſtimony be conſiderable? <hi>Fabricius,</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, though he diſſent from <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſometimes freely enough, yet ſo devout an admirer of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98192:6"/>was he, that ſomewhere he doth profeſs ſome kind of ſcrupulouſneſs to acknowledge that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of any thing, in point of nature. <hi>Caſſerius</hi> ſaith little leſs. <hi>Laurentius</hi> tells us, what opinion the world <hi>(Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophi omnes)</hi> hath always had of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſtyling him, <hi>verum naturae interpretem, ejuſdem Genium &amp; Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> &amp;c. which himſelf doth alſo ſubſcribe to: yet in the ſame place, he doth not onely complain of his ſtudied obſcurity, but alſo, as his judgement and the judgement of divers others, doth give us this account, that in his writings concerning nature in general, he was much more happy (beyond what hath ever been performed by any other:) then in them, concerning par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular natures, whether of men or beaſts: which is a great commendation, the one proceeding from the ſtrength of his brain and rational abilities; the other from ſome defect of ſenſe or better information: which no man that beleeves him to have been a man, and no more, can wonder at, or revile him for. Yet, I beleeve (and therefore take notice of it) that from this might proceed that pretty conceit of ſome men, which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth very current (I find it in your book twice or thrice) againſt <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and his Philoſophy, among many; as if his way had been, firſt, in the retitedneſs and ſecrecy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth of his contemplative brain, without the trouble and conſideration of particular objects, to frame to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>general Theories,</hi> as certain principles, or fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals; and then to determine of the true nature of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular objects by thoſe <hi>Theories.</hi> A pretty fancy I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny; and I doubt he that was the firſt author of this, may have many more of the ſame nature, if well look'd into. But I wonder that any, who can pretend ever to have look'd into <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> can entertain ſuch
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98192:7"/>fancies for real truth. For beſides thoſe books of his, which treat of the nature of particular things, altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grounded upon matter of ſenſe and experience; by all his writings it doth clearly appear, how much he did aſcribe to experimental knowledge: which to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to us the more effectually; both in his <hi>Ethicks</hi> more then once, and in his <hi>Metaphyſicks,</hi> and elſewhere too (if I be not much miſtaken) he doth, as to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of action, or ſucceſs, prefer <hi>experience</hi> without <hi>art</hi> or knowledge, before <hi>art</hi> and knowledge, without <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience;</hi> though indeed otherwiſe he doth make art of it ſelf, (that is, general rules and maxims ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at firſt upon reiterated experience) and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, which doth look into the cauſes, and can give ſatisfactory reaſons of events, more commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, then illiterate or irrational, though ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful experience. Not likely therefore that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> would frame to himſelf (which had been the project of a mad man; and to beleeve it of him little better:) <hi>general Theories,</hi> not grounded at all, upon particular obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: but that he might be miſtaken, or defective in particular obſervations, (which as long as there be inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive men in the world, may ſtill be increaſed and rectifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) is very poſſible: and thereupon his <hi>Theories,</hi> by men of judgement and ingenuity, amended or perfected. As on the other ſide, particular obſervations until they be reduced to art or <hi>theories,</hi> that is, to general rules or maxims (which is the higheſt operation of the rational faculty) are not much uſeful; which made the great oracle of Medicine to ſay, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and meer <hi>Empiricks</hi> have always been accounted dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous men.</p>
            <p>But having commended <hi>Ariſtotles Ethicks</hi> as I have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98192:7"/>done, againſt which I know objections are made by more then one; I think my ſelf bound to give you ſome further account about it. What thoſe objections are, I ſhall not now enquire, or take upon me particularly to refute: but inſtead of that, for a general anſwer to all objections that are made, or can be made, I ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the <hi>Divinity</hi> of the tenth and laſt book of the ſaid <hi>Ethicks,</hi> which as I conceive, with indifferent inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious men, is very ſufficient to make amends for all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects or defaults, if any ſuch be granted. To give you a right eſtimate of that book, according to my appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion; I cannot better then in ſaying, (though I will not ſay, that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> intended it ſo,) that it contains, allowing it but ſome variation of terms, as muſt of neceſſity be ſuppoſed, a full and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Paraphraſe,</hi> or Comment upon the firſt Pſalm; whether penned by David himſelf, or by any other, but penned of purpoſe all men grant, as an <hi>Introduction</hi> to the reſt of the Pſalms, treating of mans <hi>Summum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> or <hi>chiefeſt happienſs,</hi> wherein it doth conſiſt. To begin with that which is poſitive, or affirmative: <hi>His de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>is in the law of God:</hi> to fulfill it, as I take it, and to frame his life thereby. See <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> from the fifth Chapter of the tenth book, where he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to diſcourſe concerning <hi>beatitude,</hi> firſt he doth by good and ſolid arguments prove and evince, that it muſt conſiſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the practice, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of vertue:</hi> which in the Gentiles was ſome kind of fulfilling of the Law, as we are taught by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. But then the Pſalmiſt doth oppoſe <hi>the ſeat of the ſcornful:</hi> (ſo we tranſlate: but the Hebrew word you know, doth comprehend all <hi>mockers, jeſters, buffoons</hi> in general; and more particularly, ſuch who have an art,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98192:8"/>and make it their practiſe to turn all ſins into jeſting and merriment, as appears by <hi>Proverbs</hi> 14.9. <hi>Fools make a mock of ſin:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: it is the ſame word. <hi>Du Muis,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the place very well, That <hi>no men are more pernicious,</hi> and why:) doth oppoſe, I ſay, <hi>the ſeat</hi> of ſuch, whether <hi>mockers,</hi> or <hi>jeſters;</hi> to the practiſe or ſtudy of godlineſs and vertue. So doth <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> too, in the ſaid Chapter, very particularly. He calls them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and ſaith that ſuch are in great requeſt with great men ordinarily, becauſe of their continual facetiouſneſs and merriment: but that true happineſs is to be found, not in ſuch mirth and jollity, (or jocantneſs,) except it be for a time, by way of neceſſary relaxation; but in <hi>ſeriouſneſs:</hi> and that great men are not always beſt judges of what is right. The Pſalmiſt ſaith, that ſuch an one <hi>doth medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in the law of God day and night: Ariſtotle</hi> makes <hi>meditation,</hi> or <hi>contemplation,</hi> as he calls it, (the Hebrew word may comprehend both:) a further degree of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, whereby men (not forgetting the ſociety of men) approach neareſt unto God, and beſt reſemble him. The Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>God knoweth the way of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous:</hi> and that <hi>he ſhall be as a tree planted,</hi> &amp;c. and that <hi>whatſoever he doth ſhall proſper. Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, that ſuch an one in all <hi>probability</hi> (what could he ſay more, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Divine revelation?) is <hi>moſt beloved of God?</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.) and that God will <hi>do him good,</hi> or <hi>requite him,</hi> and that he is likely thereby to become <hi>moſt happy.</hi> Who alſo doth maintain, that this is the way for a man, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>to purchaſe immortality to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:</hi> there alſo reproving a ſpeech very rife in thoſe days among worldly men, (what may we think of them, who are ſo ſet upon the conveniences of this life that they will ſcarce allow any thing elſe to be conſiderable?)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98192:8"/>that <hi>mortals ſo born, ſhould not trouble their minds with the thought of things immortal.</hi> What think you? doth this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the note or cenſure of <hi>heathen notions?</hi> why I ſay ſo you ſhall hear by and by. But I have done with <hi>Ariſtotles Ethicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to return to the magnificent Plea of <hi>uſeful</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; much ſuch a judgement ordinary people made anciently of the moſt renowned Philoſophers, as <hi>Anaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras, Thales,</hi> and others, whom they did acknowledge to teach <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, things in themſelves <hi>excellent</hi> indeed, <hi>profound</hi> and <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <hi>uſeleſs,</hi> becauſe they contributed nothing to the uſes of this preſent life: as, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> doth ſomewhere report. This in ignorant Heathens might be tolerable: but in Chriſtians, great pretenders to knowledge, more to be wondred at. ¶ I lighted ſome years ago upon a little book intituled <hi>The reformed Schoolmaſter,</hi> &amp;c. but he treats of the reformation of <hi>Univerſities</hi> alſo, whoſe caſe he doth make ſo ſad and lamentable, as nothing can be conceived more: but yet doth give us this comfort, that if he may have his will, or deſire, they <hi>may become a thouſand times</hi> (we may bate him nine hundred; I think one hundred will ſerve) <hi>more uſeful.</hi> Indeed I never read any man that did not pretend to immediate commiſſion from God, ſpeak more magiſterially, and as it were authentically; but withal I muſt ſay, I never read any thing more whimſical and chimerical, then his <hi>Reformation</hi> doth appear unto me. He doth much reliſh of <hi>Comenius</hi> his project of making all men wiſe, and goes upon the ſame grounds. When I ſee fair Towns built in the air, and a ſure commerce between thoſe who inhabit the earth, and thoſe of the Moon, whoever they are, eſtabliſhed: I ſhall have ſome hopes that theſe projects, in caſe (which God forbid!)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98192:9"/>they be beleeved and trial made, may come to ſomewhat. Whether your Author had his <hi>Plùs ultrà</hi> from thence, I know not; but it matters not; for I think no ſober man ever denied, but that all kind of learning (with Gods bleſſing) is capable of improvement: but withall it muſt be acknowledged, that many conceited, whimſical men, as <hi>Lullus, Ramus,</hi> and the like, have projected wayes of improvement, which, if generally received, would have proved very deſtructive to learning. Amongſt other paſſages of that little book, this is one: <hi>Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in the teaching of tongues doth not tend to make them an help to traditional knowledge by the manifeſtation of real truths in ſciences, is ſuperfluous, and not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted upon, eſpecially towards children: whence followeth that the curious ſtudy of Criticiſms and obſervation of ſtyles in Authors, and of ſtrains of wit, which ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of reality in ſciences, are to be left to ſuch as delight in Vanities more then in Truths. Truth</hi> and <hi>Reality</hi> and <hi>Sciences;</hi> brave words are they not to work upon them, who either want will or wit to ſearch into the bottom of things, where in very deed, inſtead of <hi>deeds</hi> and <hi>realities</hi> nothing will be found but <hi>words?</hi> Such is his conceit, that boys and children muſt be taught things, before they be taught words or languages. His project was to advance the credit of <hi>Januae linguarum:</hi> every page almoſt hath them, and ſometimes he ſpeaks of them, as though all <hi>uſeful learning</hi> might be reduced to them. For my part, I wonder they were ever recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into any good School, except it be to caſhier good authors out of them, as needleſs: whereas I think the beſt uſe of languages is the reading of ſuch authors, not for their words onely, but for the excellency of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which in ſeveral kinds, and to ſeveral uſes, they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98192:9"/>do contain: and am very confident that where the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch authors is out of faſhion, barbariſm and groſſeſt ignorance will quickly follow. I ſpeak it of Poets as well as others. I cannot but admire at the conceit of a more conſiderable man of the ſame <hi>ſociety,</hi> (as I conceive) who would erect a new kind of <hi>Poetry,</hi> ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Scriptures, and knowledge of Nature and experiments, and ſome other heads; excluding ancient <hi>Mythology</hi> (the chief ground and foundation of ancient Poetry) as <hi>uſeleſs</hi> and <hi>fictitious.</hi> What, would he have all ancient Poets, Greek and Latin, turned out of doors? Can ſuch a thing enter into the heart of men, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the improvement of learning? This indeed <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> the Apoſtate, did maliciouſly plot and enact againſt the Chriſtians of his time, forbidding them the uſe of publick Schools, and reading of ancient Poets: which by the Fathers of the Church was looked upon as none of the leaſt perſecutions. And indeed, if ancient Poets, with their <hi>Mythology</hi> be turn'd out of doors; all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient authors muſt likewiſe, which, without a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent knowledge of ancient <hi>Poets</hi> and their <hi>Mythology</hi> (no more can ancient Fathers, Greek eſpecially, in very many places) cannot be underſtood: Of <hi>Homer</hi> particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, as elſewhere in a peculiar <hi>Diſſertation</hi> of this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, I have had occaſion more fully to declare, my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion is, that by reaſon of his antiquity, and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in many rites, ſpeeches and ſome choice ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which may be obſerved in him with the Scriptures of the old Teſtament, (obſerved by ſome learned Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentators, as <hi>Ribera</hi> and ſome others in their frequent quotations out of <hi>Homer;</hi> which alſo made learned <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellus</hi> of <hi>Sedan,</hi> ſo confidently to profeſs his opinion, or ſuſpicion at leaſt, that the Scriptures of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98192:10"/>were known to him) he doth not onely very much conduce to the right underſtanding of many ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure places in Scripture, but alſo may be ſome confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to the antiquity, and by conſequent, in ſome degree to the truth of the ſame. And ſhould I ſay, that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> was no ſtranger to <hi>Homer,</hi> (as I am ſure, he was well read in <hi>Demoſthenes</hi>) or <hi>Homer</hi> no ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to him; I hope it would be no diſparagement to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> or matter of ſcandal to any judicious, ſober man, no more then the citing of thoſe Greek Poets (<hi>Epime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nides, Menander</hi> and <hi>Aratus</hi>) their words, is or hath been: much inferiour, the beſt of them, to <hi>Homer</hi> in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſpects. And for <hi>Virgil</hi> (the beſt of Poets after <hi>Homer</hi>) that God was pleaſed to make uſe of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable wit, (whereof himſelf was the Author, or Donor) to celebrate the coming of his Son our Saviour, into the world; hath been the opinion of ſome ancient and later Chriſtians; men of excellent judgement. But again, a great part of the ancient <hi>Mythology,</hi> though with much <hi>Sophiſtication</hi> generally, being derived from the Scriptures, as learned men anciently, and the moſt learned of this latter age have thought, and thereupon taken great pains, ſome of them to trace it to its firſt original, ſuppoſing that the Scriptures among the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and judicious, would receive no ſmall confirmation by their labours herein; how can it now be <hi>diſmiſſed,</hi> or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheered, without ſome wrong to the Scriptures; which never more (in this viſible ſad increaſe of Atheiſm every where) wanted all kind of confirmation!</p>
            <p>But much more did I wonder at another paſſage of the ſame Author, in a more conſiderable ſubject then <hi>Poetry</hi> is. It is where he treats of the <hi>Schoolmen;</hi> favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably enough I muſt confeſs, as when he ſaith, <hi>If they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98192:10"/>would be content with any thing leſs then an Empire in learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we would grant them very much.</hi> I think they are much to blame, if no leſs will content them: and they as much who uphold them upon that ſcore. All the reſt that follows this is very moderate and reaſonable. But the concluſion, <hi>And yet I ſhould not doubt, (if it were not ſomewhat improper to the preſent diſcourſe) to prove, that even in Divinity it ſelf, they are not ſo neceſſary, as they are reputed to be; and that all, or moſt of our religious controverſies, may be as well decided by plain reaſon, and by conſiderations which may be fetched from the religion of mankind, the nature of government and humane ſociety, and Scripture it ſelf, as by the multitude of Authorities and ſubtilties of Diſputes, which have been heretofore in uſe:</hi>] this I do not underſtand. According to ordinary conſtruction, the ſenſe is obvious enough; but a ſenſe ſo amazing, that it is not credible. It is well known that before the late troubles, a <hi>Noble-man</hi> of this Realm wrote a book intituled <hi>De Veritate:</hi> the end and drift where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was, out of the Religions of mankind to extract a Religion that ſhould need no Chriſt. And though they that licenſed it did not apprehend it ſo, it ſeems; (I did at firſt ſight) yet himſelf afterwards during the troubles in his <hi>Epiſtola ad Sacerdotes,</hi> printed with the reſt of his works, did pretty well unmask himſelf and openly ſhewed what opinion he had of Chriſtianity. Since him it is well known, that ſome body hath taken ſome pains to attemperate Chriſtianity to the laws of every Countrey, and commands of Supreme Powers: and this he doth ground, or endeavour to ground, (not as the other, who did ſcorn them) upon divers paſſages of <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</hi> What can this import, in ordinary conſtruction, but a new Religion? Eſpecially when it is ſaid, that the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98192:11"/>
               <hi>controverſies of it may be decided by plain reaſon, as well as by the multitude of Authorities, and ſubtilties of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, which have been heretofore in uſe.</hi> For the <hi>controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of Chriſtianity</hi> every body knows began in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time, (as doth appear by their writings, a great part of which is ſpent on that argument) and being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted and increaſed in ſucceeding ages (according to old <hi>Simeons</hi> prophecy concerning Chriſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Luke 2.34. the effect of which prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, as alſo of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls, <hi>Oportet haereſes eſſe,</hi> will conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to the worlds end) by an hoſt of Hereticks and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, who have been happily repreſſed and repelled by thoſe bleſſed Fathers, and authority of general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils and Provincial, which every age afforded, whoſe excellent works by a ſingular providence of God, are yet for the moſt part, extant: who can expect, or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that any other courſe can be available to the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of true Chriſtianity? And certainly, when and where men (whether through force, or want of good learning) ſhall be made uncapable to uphold their faith with ſound reaſoning and diſputing (which they call <hi>wrangling</hi>) what will be the iſſue, or who will get by it, any man may gueſs.
<q>Hoc Ithacus velit, &amp; magno mercentur Atridae:</q> I ſhall ſay no more. I profeſs ſincerely, that I can make no other ſenſe of the words: I ſay therefore, I do not underſtand them. Yet I muſt acknowledge, that the ſame Author doth elſewhere ſpeak of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the chief myſteries of it, very reverently and zealouſly; much abhorring, or profeſſing to abhor all innovations in it, or that it ſhould ſuffer in any thing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98192:11"/>by <hi>Experimental Philoſophie;</hi> yet even there, he doth not onely fetch the firſt eſtabliſhment of it, (which to me ſounds but odly, to ſay no more) from Experiments, calling <hi>miracles Divine Experiments:</hi> but alſo doth commend unto us, men of <hi>honeſty, trade and buſineſs:</hi> (ſuch as deal in <hi>Experiments,</hi> he doth mean certainly) as the beſt upholders, or <hi>teſtifiers</hi> of it; rather then men <hi>of craft and ſpeculation:</hi> alleadging to that end the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Apoſtles: who indeed, moſt of them, by their profeſſion at firſt, (and ſuch choſen then of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe by a ſingular providence) were no better then illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate tradeſmen and labourers: but (which he doth not tell us) were not onely long taught by Chriſt their Maſter; but alſo immediately and miraculouſly inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (beſides the power of miracles given them) by God, before they began to preach the Goſpel unto men: none of which things, I think, belong to the modern profeſſors of <hi>Experimental philoſophie.</hi> By men of <hi>craft and ſpeculation,</hi> by the drift and tenor of his diſcourſe he can intend no other then ancient Fathers, and School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and late learned Writers of <hi>Controverſies.</hi> Now ſuch an aſſertion, I conceive not onely prejudicial, but very deſtructive to true Religion and Chriſtianity. Theſe things how to be reconciled, I profeſs I know not. To ſpeak therefore as moderately as I can; I ſaid, and ſay again, I do not underſtand him. If you do, I ſhall be beholding to you to help me.</p>
            <p>But I have not yet done with our <hi>School-Reformer. Whence followeth,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that the curious ſtudy of Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſms and obſervation of ſtyles in Authors,</hi> &amp;c. And where have we a Commentator almoſt, either upon the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture (beſides thoſe lately collected and ſet out in many volumes, under the name of <hi>Criticks</hi>) or upon any good
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98192:12"/>Author, Greek or Latin, that is not put to his <hi>criticiſms</hi> ſometimes, and <hi>obſervation of ſtyles?</hi> which in very deed (obſervation of ſtyles) is as conſiderable a ſtudy for the preſervation and vindication of all kind of truth, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſacred, (all truth is, more or leſs) or civil, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in whole kingdoms and Commonweals are much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned ſometimes, as any ſtudy can be. And what think you of <hi>Longinus,</hi> whoſe treatiſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>de ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi dicendi genere,</hi> (not many years ago ſet out by a very learned and worthy man, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Langbaine,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voſt of <hi>Qucens</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford</hi>) hath been ſo much commended and admired by learned men; when he ſaith: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: ſo diametrically oppoſite? God bleſs the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities, and Univerſity-Libraries, from ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers!</p>
            <p>I now return to your Book; where I meet with an Objection againſt old learning and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> particularly, which is made by more then one, but by your Author (as he doth not want words to ſet out his matter to the beſt advantage) preſſed very vigorouſly: which is in his own words, <hi>that it hath kept him from ſurveying the works of God, that magnifie and diſcover their Author, from which onely the true Philoſophie is obtained.</hi> Good God! can any body that hath but looked into <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> though never ſo perfunctorily (except it be by the help of ſome glaſs that repreſents things quite contrary) ſay ſo? But he goes on: <hi>And the zeal I have for Almighty God his glory diſcovered in his creatures hath inſpired me with ſome ſmartneſs and ſeverity againſt heathen notions, which have ſo unhappily diverted learned men from the ſtudy of Gods great book, univerſal nature; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently robbed him of that honour, and thoſe acclamations
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98192:12"/>that are due to him for thoſe admirable reſults of his wiſdom and goodneſs.</hi> This Author (I ſaid before) doth not want words: he can expreſs himſelf ſmartly enough up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on very light occaſions: which in a good cauſe is no ſmall commendation: but otherwiſe I ſhould have been very ſuſpicious, if not confident, he had borrowed this goodly language from ſome profane Chymiſt, ſuch as our <hi>Robert Fludd</hi> was, with whom ſuch profeſſions of zeal for the glory of God are very frequent and ordinary: and to that end to ſet out his glory in its greateſt Iuſtre, doth propoſe unto us the conſideration of the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers ſtone,</hi> applying all or moſt myſteries of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to it, as that wherein onely, or chiefly, the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Power and Wiſdom of God is to be ſeen and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: ſo that in very truth, his zeal was more for the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers ſtone,</hi> then <hi>God;</hi> or, the <hi>Philoſophers ſtone,</hi> a God of his own making, for which he was ſo zealous. But this I cannot averr upon mine own credit. For though his books, when I was very young &amp; curious enough to pry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to every thing that promiſed ſomewhat more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, did offer themſelves to me in Book-ſellers ſhops; yet I profeſs I could never diſpenſe ſo much with my reaſon or conſcience, as to read long, where I found nothing but what I judged in a high degree both impertinent and blaſphemous. I muſt therefore diſcharge my ſelf upon learned <hi>Gaſsendus,</hi> who together with <hi>Merſennus,</hi> will I think make good what I have ſaid of him to the full. But indeed it is the common language of all extravagant Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts: they all, as many as I have ſeen that are ſuch, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon the ſame thing. Neither is it their plea, or lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage onely; but of all men generally, who profeſſing Chriſtianity would raiſe admiration, by broaching un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of myſteries. There be men in the world we know,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98192:13"/>who maintain with much ſhew of zeal and holineſs, that the ſtars of heaven are ſo many ſignificant Characters and Hieroglyphicks, there placed by God of purpoſe the better to manifeſt his Wiſdom to the beholders, and from the right reading &amp; underſtanding whereof greateſt myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries depend. Neither want they ſome places of Scripture, which they miſerably abuſe to countenance the buſineſs. <hi>Gafarell</hi> is a great abetter of this <hi>heavenly</hi> myſtery. The <hi>Glory of God,</hi> and the <hi>Wiſdom of God</hi> here alſo muſt be the pretence: which to oppoſe (in very truth, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult and product of ſick brains hunting after Novelties) how can it be leſs then <hi>heatheniſh</hi> profaneneſs and impiety. Yes, if you will beleeve them. But granting, as I do, and all men will, that well conſider of it, that <hi>praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Deum quaelibet herba:</hi> that there is nothing in nature, in ſight ſo inconſiderable, but may give an intelligent man matter and occaſion to admire and magnifie the Power and Wiſdom of God. Is the conſideration of all thoſe, (mentioned in this book) or like curioſities, <hi>the Great Book</hi> of God, from which men muſt learn the great Power and Wiſdom of the Creator? It is ordinary enough indeed (obſerved by many) among men to wonder at nothing, though never ſo wonderful and admirable, but what is unuſual, far fetch'd, and ſeldom ſeen. Many who never took notice of either Sun or Moon, and the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of either; the viciſſitudes of the year; the flux and reflux of the Sea and the like, to admire them, or God in them, becauſe daily and ordinary: will yet gaze with wonder at a Meteor, the ſhooting of a Star, as they call it, or an <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> and the like. But they are not thought the wiſeſt of men, that are of that temper. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> I hope, underſtood wherein the <hi>Glory of God</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, and for what God himſelf would be magnified by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98192:13"/>men principally, as well as another. We do not find by any of thoſe admirable Pſalms that are written of that ſubject, that any other works of God are ſpecified, but thoſe that are very viſible to all men, ſufficient alſo to make God viſible to them, who have ſo much grace (which wicked <hi>Epicurus</hi> had not) to beleeve that they were not made to eat and drink, and to enjoy the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this life; but to obſerve the works of God, and to glorifie him therefore. And beſides thoſe admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Works of the Creation, which many now (too many) taught by <hi>Epicurus</hi> and his mates, are apt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe and vilifie, as being the works not of a wiſe <hi>God,</hi> but blinde <hi>atoms:</hi> there be other works of God not leſs to be admired: and thoſe be the Works of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Government of the World; which the ſame Pſalmiſt in his 107. Pſalm, doth very particularly inſiſt upon, and doth adviſe all men to conſider well: <hi>they that are wiſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>will conſider theſe things;</hi> implying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, as I conceive, that the conſideration of thoſe things will make a man <hi>wiſe;</hi> ſo that it is very poſſible, if we beleeve him, for a man to be both wiſe and religious; a great admirer of Gods works, his Goodneſs, Wiſdom and Power; who never underſtood, or ſhall underſtand any of thoſe things, never known before, as we are told here. After all this, we need leſs wonder, that your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour (I pray excuſe me, that I call him ſo, not that I think you are bound to maintain whatſoever he ſaith, but becauſe I had him firſt from you) ſhould appropriate <hi>ſubſtantial wiſdom</hi> to this kind of Experimental Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy: though I hope he doth not intend thereby <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in our Engliſh, <hi>found wiſdom:</hi> intended by <hi>Solomon</hi> of the true fear and ſanctifying knowledge of God, to which the promiſes of eternal life are annexed:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98192:14"/>from whence it would follow, that according to him, none can be ſaved but by this way of Philoſophy. But I will be more charitable then to think he could for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get himſelf ſo much, though ſome may juſtly ſtumble at ſuch ſuperlative expreſſions, and his Philoſophy (with ſober men) more likely to loſe then to gain by them. For though I deny not (I ſaid it before, and ſay it again) that the ſtudy of Nature to a man that hath grace, and is well grounded in the principles of Faith, may afford ſomewhat beſide the known and moſt viſible works of God, as Sun and ſtars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (wherein God, as the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and wiſeſt heathens did teach, is moſt viſible) to the <hi>glory of God,</hi> and acknowledgment of his <hi>Power and Wiſdom:</hi> yet truly I think they do not go a right way, either to improve the <hi>Glory of God,</hi> or humane wiſdom, who do ſo magnifie this ſtudy, as though there were no other wiſdom in the world to be thought of, or purſued after; that make it the onely <hi>uſeful,</hi> true, ſolid learning, to which they would have all Schools and Univerſities fitted, and to which the Nobility of the land are invited, as to the employment of all employments moſt worthy their entertainment. I think the reading of Hiſtories, and military exerciſes (among which <hi>hunting</hi> is reckoned) which may fit them to do their King and Countrey ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; to maintain the credit of their Anceſtors; will much more become them, then attending on furnaces, or raking into the entrals of men, or beaſts, to find ſomewhat, which it may be will never make them much wiſer when they know it, nor ever prove of any great uſe. Other employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which exerciſe the body, beſide that they are more creditable, they preſerve health alſo, and keep the body in a conſtant readineſs for more neceſſary employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if occaſion be. And though reading of hiſtories
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98192:14"/>doth not exerciſe the body, yet it may fit them for action; and if they be read with delight, they may contribute much, not onely to compoſe the mind, in greateſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbances; but alſo to help, yea cure the body, when nothing elſe will. So it happened to two great Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, (<hi>Bodinus</hi> is my Author at this time, and he is one that may be truſted in matter of hiſtory) <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> and <hi>Ferdinandus</hi> Kings of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> who when no Phyſick or Phyſicians could do them good toward the recovery of their health; did own it, (under God) the one to the reading of <hi>Livy;</hi> and the other of <hi>Quintus Curtius.</hi> The ſame is reported of <hi>Laurentius Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices,</hi> (that excellent Prince, both learned himſelf, and a great promoter of learning) as the ſame <hi>Bodinus</hi> doth more particularly give account.</p>
            <p>I could tell you ſome ſtories of my ſelf, how ſtudious I have been from my youth, of the knowledge of nature in general: not to commend my proficiency unto you, (I have no reaſon, which I may partly impute to my ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in many kinds) but probably to ſatisfie you, that I am ſtill a great lover and honourer of it. But when I read what mighty things ſome men promiſe themſelves and others of their way: what braggings and boaſtings: what contempt of all other things: it makes me think of the Hebrew proverb, <hi>Non volentis, neque currentis, &amp;c.</hi> whether here alſo, not conſiderable: that is, whether it be probable, that God will give a bleſſing to ſuch a violent purſuit, that will not keep within its bounds, but (as the matter is propoſed unto us by ſome writers; for I go no farther, nor can) doth aſpire to an abſolute Soveraignty over all, that in ſo many ages of the world hath been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>uſeful</hi> learning and knowledge. A man indeed may plauſibly ſuppoſe, that if rareſt things and moſt bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98192:15"/>(ſome of them) as the invention of the <hi>Compaſs:</hi> of <hi>Printing:</hi> of <hi>Guns</hi> and <hi>Powder:</hi> of a <hi>new world,</hi> and the like, have been found out by the inquiſitiveneſs, or induſtry of ſome private men; what may we not hope of the joynt labours of an whole nation, all men being invited and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, rich and poor, learned and unlearned? Yet let it be remembred withall, that there is a ſupreme cauſe, which hath a ſecret influence into all the endeavours of men, to promote or to put back; to bleſs or to blaſt, as it pleaſeth. God knows his own time, and when that time is come, one ſingle man ſhall do more perchance, then a combination of many thouſands, at another time. A man might give a probable reaſon, now it is done, why God would reſerve the diſcovery of the New world, lately found out, to theſe times, and why it was a very ſeaſonable, for his glory, and the truth of his promiſes, diſcovery then. I have ſaid ſomewhat of it elſewhere, which I will not trouble you with here. Now, in order to that diſcovery, and what enſued upon it; the <hi>Compaſs</hi> and the invention of <hi>gun-powder</hi> was not expedient one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but in a manner neceſſary. The invention of <hi>Printing</hi> did much promote learning, and learning (good <hi>uſeful</hi> learning) that <hi>reformation,</hi> which God intended in his Church. Every thing hath its proper time, and that time is a ſecret of Gods diſpenſation, which muſt be left to God, though man may ſometimes not improbably gueſs, or conjecture. <hi>Baptiſta Porta</hi> was a man that had as great helps and encouragements to ſeek into the ſecrets of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as ever any man ſince <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> had. He began betimes, he was not much above fifteen years of age (as if Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence had deſigned him for ſuch a work) when he began to appear in Print, as a Naturaliſt; and his work was ſo well accepted of in the world that it was (ſet out in Latin
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98192:15"/>at firſt, as I conceive) ſoon tranſlated, himſelf tells us, into the French, Italian, Spaniſh and Arabick Tongues. From that time for thirty five years he followed it with aſſiduous and indefatigable induſtry. He was a man of ſome means himſelf, it ſeems, and had large contributions from great men, Cardinals and others: he made his houſe a kind of Academy for all men that had any curioſity that way: and himſelf travelled divers countreys to confer with others. He neglected not Tradeſmen and Artificers; and whither he could not convey his perſon, he did addreſs himſelf by letters, with much earneſtneſs and inſtancy: and he profeſſeth, that it was always his greateſt care not to take things upon truſt, but to make trial firſt himſelf, if poſſible, of what he doth deliver for truth to others. What might not be expected from ſuch a man? I will not ſay, he hath done nothing; I ſhould do him and the truth great wrong if I did. He hath certainly many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, which were firſt publiſhed and perfected by himſelf; and I think it were a very good work, if ſome men ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and well qualified that way would upon trial declare, what they find in him certain and unqueſtionable, and what otherwiſe, that ſo we might know what men may certainly truſt to. But what ever he hath done, to make the moſt of it, will not amount, for the admirableneſs and uſefulneſs of it, to what hath been invented, or found by ſome one ſingle man: from whence I conclude, that greateſt ſecrets will not be extorted from God, by a kind of violence and preſumption, but that man doing his part in his calling, either as a <hi>Mechanick,</hi> or <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> God muſt be left to his own will and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>And whereas a long Inventory is given by your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, of things lately diſcovered, that were not known to the Ancients; I think it would have been the part of an
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98192:16"/>impartial man, to have told us at the ſame time, that we have loſt ſome things alſo known to the Ancients, and what they are, which happily might deſerve as much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect; ſo much at leaſt as not to be paſſed in ſilence. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch things (beſides what is collected by <hi>Pancirollus,</hi> in a Treatiſe of that Argument) have been obſerved by more then one, Phyſicians and others, all which I cannot call to mind ſuddenly. One thing may be <hi>cutting for the ſtone in the kidneys,</hi> which in <hi>Hippocrates</hi> time was practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (I have read it in more then one) with good ſucceſs; but now, and ever ſince <hi>Galens</hi> time (for which ſome blame him) loſt and forgotten. To this, divers other things are added by learned Phyſicians, as that which they call <hi>diſſectio in Empyematibus: exuſtio in jecoris humoribus: cranii perforatio in aqua cerebri: ſectio ſupra oculum in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſionibus: extractio aquae intercutis:</hi> which laſt, though ſome venture upon in theſe days alſo, yet it is obſerved that few or none eſcape;, for want of the right way. To theſe I make no queſtion but many more might be added, and I am ſure I have met with more in their books, which I do not at this time remember. Whether <hi>Galen</hi> had any knowledge of the <hi>venae lacteae,</hi> and the like, I know not; but I am confident he had that knowledge of all the <hi>muſcles, ſinews, arteries, fibers</hi> and the like, and their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per uſe in every part of the body, (as doth appear by thoſe admirable books he hath written of that ſubject) as I think few Phyſicians have at this day: of which know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge what uſe he made may appear by one ſtory, which I remember to have read in him. A young boy belonging to a great man in <hi>Rome,</hi> had received ſome hurt in his body, by a fall out of a Coach, or Chariot, ſuch as they had in thoſe days. The boy was very dear to his Maſter, who ſpared no coſt to have him perfectly cured. Many Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98192:16"/>and Chirurgeons were employed: but for all they could do, two fingers of one of his hands continued as it were dead. <hi>Galen</hi> happened to come to <hi>Rome</hi> about that time, and was invited by the great man to ſee the boy; he did, and being well informed of all particulars of his fall, he preſently took away all that he found applied to the ſick fingers, and applied ſomewhat to one of the bones of his back, whereupon the fingers immediately, or ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter recovered their former uſe &amp; ſtrength. Yet I know <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalius</hi> made it his buſineſs to contradict <hi>Galen</hi> as much as he could: but other later Anatomiſts have defended him; and <hi>Veſalius,</hi> though generally acknowledged an excellent A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomiſt, hath found ſome who have taken as much pains to contradict him. It is my opinion, that there is ſcarce any art, or faculty, wherein we do not come ſhort of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents. Indeed their induſtry, much provoked by the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of rewards, was greater generally; that cannot be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Painting, Carving</hi> the <hi>Statuaria,</hi> are in a manner loſt, in compariſon of what they had attained to. So is the Art of <hi>Coyning</hi> of money, as uſed in the beſt times of the Roman Empire: beſt Writers and Artificers of theſe days ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it. So is <hi>Muſick. Ludovicus Vives</hi> (beſides <hi>Pancirollus</hi> before named) was of that opinion, I am ſure: and there is ſo much to be ſaid, that it is ſo; that I do not ſee how it can be doubted, or denied by any man. The ſecret of thoſe <hi>eternal Lamps,</hi> as we may call them, found in divers ancient graves, though ſo much, by more then one, hath been written of them, continues a ſecret to this day: and I doubt whether modern <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> ſo much admired by ſome men, afford any thing that deſerves more admiration. Doth any body pretend in theſe days to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> as <hi>Archimedes</hi> did? What would not men, Kings and Princes give for one of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions?
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98192:17"/>But I have ſaid more of him very lately.</p>
            <p>Hitherto nothing hath been ſaid to impair the credit or uſefulneſs of <hi>Natural</hi> or <hi>Experimental</hi> Philoſophy: but that we would not allow it to uſurp upon all other learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as not conſiderable in compariſon. Now I crave leave to tell you, that it is (as all good things, more or leſs) very apt to be abuſed and to degenerate into <hi>Atheiſm.</hi> Men that are much fixed upon matter and ſecundary cauſes and ſenſual objects, if great care be not taken, may in time, (there be many examples) and by degrees forget that there be ſuch things in the world as <hi>Spirits,</hi> ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces really exiſting and of great power, though not viſible, or palpable by their nature; forget I ſay, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcredit <hi>ſupernatural operations:</hi> and at laſt, that there is a God, and that their ſouls are immortal. This is a great precipice; and the contempt of all other learning an ill preſage. I cannot tell what ſhould make the <hi>Metaphyſicks,</hi> that noble ſcience, ſo deſpicable unto them: them I mean, who have declared themſelves and their opinion of it. Indeed, they have nothing to do with the ſenſes, and may be called <hi>Notional:</hi> but real though, and the more abſtracted from the ſenſes, therefore the more divine. What a coil hath been kept with <hi>Carteſius's Ego cogito:</hi> to prove the immortality of the ſoul thereby? How much more effectually may it be proved by the capacity men have of <hi>Metaphyſical</hi> contemplations, or the conſideration of <hi>Ens quatenus Ens,</hi> ſo abſtracted from all that is ſenſual and material? For my part, I profeſs, (next the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our faith) I never have been more ſenſible of the immortality of humane ſouls, then when I had the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to be converſant with that noble Science. To me truly it is no good ſigne, that this ſecondary kind of The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ology, or Divinity, (and ſo called by many you know)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98192:17"/>is ſo out of requeſt. But Natural Philoſophy I grant, is more taking and bewitching generally: there is a plain reaſon for it: and though cryed up for the onely <hi>uſeful</hi> knowledge, yet if well conſidered, it may be found ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, to have much more of pleaſure and curioſity in it then uſe and profit; even in that ſenſe (for what is truly <hi>uſeful</hi> and <hi>profitable,</hi> or moſt <hi>uſeful</hi> and <hi>profitable,</hi> is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther queſtion) which they intend.</p>
            <p>Yet (Give me leave, I pray, to tell you this pretty ſtory by the way) if we muſt, or may beleeve every thing that is written by men addicted to this way, we may find won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful effects of it, even to <hi>moralize</hi> men; which indeed is the beſt uſe of any worldly thing which can be made. <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> in the life of <hi>Peyreskius</hi> a right worthy man, and great Patron of all kind of learning, hath this ſtory of him: <hi>Dicebat verò nihil ſibi unquam animi regendi perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem aequè feciſſe, &amp;c.</hi> Give me leave to tell it you in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, though I know you a great Maſter of the Latin Tongue. <hi>Peyreskius,</hi> it ſeems, had ſhut in a <hi>microſcope,</hi> a <hi>louſe</hi> and a <hi>flie</hi> together; how they fell out <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> doth not tell us; but it ſeems they were not long together but they began to quarrel and to fight, and <hi>Peyreskius</hi> was a ſpectator of the combat: where he obſerved, that the <hi>louſe</hi> (the more paſſionate of the two, it ſeems) was ſo diſtracted and vexed, that after reiterated goings to and fro, (whether as a coward, to run away; or for the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of freſh onſets he doth not tell us) all the bloud of his head was ſunk into his tail; the effect he ſaith, of a great paſſion (he was ſtriving for his life, a very natural paſſion this) and very prejudicial to the ſtate of the body. By this ſight <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> tells us <hi>Peyreskius</hi> profited more to rule his paſſions in the reſt of his life, then he had done by any thing he had heard, or read before. This is the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98192:18"/>ſtory: which, when I conſider the Worth and Nobleneſs of the man, of whom it is written, I could wiſh that <hi>Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſendus</hi> had left out: What? <hi>Peyreskius,</hi> ſo learned, ſo wiſe a man, to profit more by the ſight of ſuch a combat, and the demeanour of the <hi>louſe</hi> in it, in a thing of ſuch conſequence to a mans life, then he had done by the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſo many Philoſophers, who have written ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently of that ſubject, (and among other things, have not omitted this very particular, the ghaſtly countenance and deformity of a man in paſſion, and the diſeaſes and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal accidents it doth expoſe him to) or the precepts and perſwaſions of the <hi>Word of God,</hi> always divine; but in this Argument, even to humane reaſon, moſt excellent and ſingular? <hi>Galen</hi> indeed, I remember, hath a ſtory, how by ſome chance being an eye-witneſs to the impatience of a man, who becauſe when he knocked at a door was anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, The party was not at home, fell into ſuch a rage and fury, both in words and actions, as no mad man could out do: it made ſuch impreſſion in him that he was the better for it all his life after. This is ſomewhat like, as the ſight of a drunken man may work upon an ingenuous youth, to make him abhor drunkenneſs for ever. But that the ſight of the <hi>bloud of a louſe,</hi> paſſing from the head to the tail, (which perchance is no ſuch extraordinary thing in a <hi>louſe</hi>) ſhould be of ſuch force with ſo brave a man, as <hi>Peyreskius</hi> was, above all that he had ever read or obſerved upon that ſubject; and that he ſhould as it were in thankfulneſs to the <hi>louſe,</hi> make an acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it to his friends, I have not faith enough to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> in this: but rather beleeve, or ſuſpect that <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> made this pretty ſtory, either upon occaſion of ſomewhat that <hi>Peyreskius</hi> had told him of a <hi>louſe</hi> or a <hi>flie,</hi> but not to that purpoſe; or of purpoſe to gratifie
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98192:18"/>ſome friends, who would be glad to hear what uſe can be made, even in point of life and manners, of a <hi>microſcope.</hi> But you will ſay perchance, doth not wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> ſay, <hi>Go to the Ant thou ſluggard?</hi> &amp;c. Yes, he doth indeed, but to the ſluggard: <hi>pigro,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: words of great weight: as elſewhere I have ſhewed: not to ſuch a man as <hi>Peyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skius</hi> was; nor as if <hi>Ants</hi> by their example could teach men, what their own reaſon and the good inſtructions of other men (beſide the Scripture) could not: but to make ſuch wretches more ſenſible of their degenerating into brutiſhneſs; when they ſee ſuch acts of reaſon performed by thoſe creatures by meer inſtinct of nature, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their own reaſon, nor the reaſon (good inſtruction) of other men can perſwade them to. Beſides, he ſends them to what will not require the labour, or curioſity of much obſervation, or inquiſition; but to that which is very obvious to all men. Add, that Ants certainly, are more noble creatures then <hi>Lice,</hi> becauſe they live in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and have a form of government among themſelves, which doth preſuppoſe ſome kind of reaſon, or ſomewhat anſwerable to reaſon in men. To this purpoſe, I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber I have read the deſcription of a City made (I cannot ſay built) by <hi>Ants;</hi> the Author whereof is no leſs a man then a learned Biſhop, as by the elegancy of his ſtyle I gueſs him to have been. Learned <hi>Gillius</hi> I am ſure is not more accurate in the deſcription of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> then he is (for the bigneſs of it: for I would not have you think, that it is any thing near ſo big as <hi>Conſtantinople</hi>) in the deſcription of this <hi>city</hi> of Ants. He hath the dimenſions of the longitude and latitude of every ſtreet in it, and the particulars of ſome publick places belonging to it, with much accurateneſs. He writes it in good earneſt; and for my part I beleeve him; though if you do not, I ſhall not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98192:19"/>account you an Infidel for it. Yet I do not deny, but ſome good may come, even in matters of life, by the obſervation of ſome actions in brutes: but as good, ſo evil alſo, when men not knowing, or forgetting whoſe image they bare, are more apt (ſo the greater number) to proſtitute their reaſon to meer nature, then to rectifie nature by right rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. We read in <hi>Herodotus</hi> of a people who thought car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal copulation lawful enough in their Temples, becauſe they obſerved that beaſts that were brought to and kept in Temples for ſacrifices, made no conſcience of it. So <hi>Pontus Houterus</hi> of <hi>Delph</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> grounding eſpecially upon the cuſtom of brute beaſts, would infer the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>inceſt</hi> among men: <hi>Non illa</hi> (natura) <hi>matrem ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcit, non ſororem, &amp;c.</hi> which is very horrible. And I could name ſome body elſe, who doth not ſay much leſs; but for the reputation he hath in the world I will ſpare his name. And what will you ſay to him, who out of his ſtudy (he ſaith, not very buſie then certainly:) having obſerved the carriage of a Sparrow (the moſt laſcivious of all creatures, as is obſerved by ſome Naturaliſts) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards its mate, <hi>(vicies repetito coitu, &amp; indè ex languore ad terram decidente)</hi> began to quarrel with God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>(en ſortem iniquam, hoc paſſeribus datum, negatum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus!)</hi> that he had made him a man and not a Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. It were to be wiſhed that they that are deſtined to the ſtudy of Nature, were ſuch as have attained by their years to ordinary diſcretion, and are well grounded in Religion: I know not what we may expect of wanton <hi>Boyes,</hi> whom ſome would have trained up in thoſe ſtudies be times.</p>
            <p>But another danger is: may not a man go too far in this ſtudy, and overvalue his progreſs ſo far, as to think no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out of his reach? It was a noble attempt (as to man) of them that built, or would have built the tower of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98192:19"/>whoſe top might reach to Heaven:</hi> It is not likely they could be ſo ſimple, as to think really they ſhould reach to Heaven by it: they might think they ſhould be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what nearer perchance; and however, get a name among men in after ages, that they that built ſuch a <hi>tower,</hi> were ſomewhat above men. But confuſion was their reward. I have no reaſon to be againſt the <hi>Art of flying,</hi> if diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verable by humane induſtry; I have reaped the pleaſures of it in my dreams more then once; and I thought no pleaſure comparable to it, though but in a dream. Yet I doubt it may have ſomewhat of the Babyloniſh preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption in the eyes of God; and that ſuch high curioſities are ſo far from being <hi>uſeful,</hi> that they may be dangerous. <hi>Alas aut expectare, aut ſperare, intemperantis &amp; naturae ſuae conditionem ignorantis animi eſt:</hi> is <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the matter, which I hope will excuſe me. Yet I muſt confeſs, I think there is leſs offence in the conceit of <hi>Artificial flying</hi> then in the conceit of <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mim,</hi> being an <hi>Artificial Chymical preparation,</hi> whoever was the Author of it; which I think deſerved to be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured as impious: and if ſuch liberty be taken, or allowed, I know not how far it may proceed, or how ſoon <hi>Robert Flud</hi> his blaſphemies, which <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> hath cenſured and confuted may be received for <hi>uſeful</hi> truths or learning.</p>
            <p>But I have done. What I had to except againſt the book you brought me, I have told you. I muſt now thank you for it. For in very truth, his <hi>Divinity</hi> at the end, which is ſomewhat myſtical (I hope I do not underſtand it) and thoſe two particulars, his contempt of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and his cenſuring all other learning beſides <hi>Experimental</hi> Philoſophy, and what tendeth to it as <hi>uſeleſs,</hi> and meer <hi>wrangling</hi> and <hi>diſputing,</hi> excepted: I have read the reſt, wherein he doth give us an exact account of late diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98192:20"/>with much pleaſure. For though I think many ages may paſs before the uſe of many of thoſe particulars is known; yet <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath taught me, (and he proves it excellently) that nothing can be in nature ſo mean, or ſo vile, but deſerves to be taken notice of, and will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford to an ingenious ſpeculative man, matter of pleaſure and delight.</p>
            <p>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, I know your relations to ſome of eminent worth and piety in that <hi>Honourable Society,</hi> whom though we have not the happineſs to know otherwiſe, then by the fame of their writings; yet we honour their worth as much as you do. I hope you do not think any thing I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten can reflect upon any ſuch. No, nor upon any others, farther then in thoſe particulars I have mentioned. You know my condition, and Judge I hope ſo charitably, that I would not go out of the World, but in perfect love and charity with all men. As long as I live continue unto me, I pray, the comfort of your love, and good opinion, who am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your affectionate Brother, and humble Servant, MERIC CASAUBON.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98192:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
